Amazon Foundation papers, 1990-2002 (bulk 1998-2008)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Amazon Foundation papers, 1990-2002
MS 425
Amazon Foundation
Papers, 1990-2002 (bulk: 1998-2002). This collection contains material relating to the Amazon Foundation, a feminist and anti-discriminatory philanthropic organization that provided grants to community building projects with a focus on improving the lives of girls and women in Southern Arizona. Materials include administrative documents: such as financial, informational and organizational materials, award documents: including correspondence and printed materials on grants and scholarships, and photographic material: including photographs of foundation and grantee events and a photo album. The bulk of the material is in English.
4.25 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None
Historical Note
The Amazon Foundation is a feminist organization that provided grants to promote progressive social change and the betterment of the lives of girls and women in Southern Arizona as well as women and girls of color, lesbians, gay men, bisexuals, transgender individuals and people with disabilities. The Amazon Foundation was founded in the 90s by philanthropist Kristie Graham who wished to use her wealth to effect social change. The foundation refined its mission in 2001 to focus their grant efforts on activist organizations with the hope that by targeting the root of social injustice much of the problems of equal access, economic justice, and violence would be solved. Direct-service programs in the borderlands area were retained due to a lack of services in that region. After founder and funder Kristie Graham relocated from Tucson in 2002 the Amazon Foundation closed its doors.
Organization
This collection is organized into 3 series
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1994-2002
Subseries 1: Financial Documents, 1994-2001
Subseries 2: Informational Documents, 1998-2002
Subseries 3: Organizational Documents, 1994-2002
Series 2: Award Files, 1990-2002
Subseries 1: Grants, 1990-2002
Subseries 2: Scholarships, 1994-2002
Series 3: Photographic Material, 2001
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1990-2002 (bulk 1998-2002). This collection contains the papers of the Amazon Foundation documenting its involvement in grant giving in Southern Arizona including Tucson. The bulk of the documents are grant files which contain the foundation's documents on each of their grantees. Included in these files are grant inquiries, proposals, approvals and rejections, programs, photographs, and correspondence. Also included are administrative documents such as financial forms and statements, informational materials about Amazon Foundation programs, and internal organizational documents such as committee notes and by laws. Photographic materials are also included in the collection and document foundation and grantee functions and activities. Most of the collection is in English with some Spanish documents.
Access Terms
Tucson (Ariz.) -- Charities.
Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations -- United States -- Political activity.
Women in community organization -- United States.
Feminism -- United States.
Social action -- United States.
Container List
- Administrative Files 1994-2002
  Arrangement: Alphabetical. This series contains the administrative documents of the Amazon Foundation. It is divided into three subseries.
  Financial Documents: Contains documents of a financial nature including tax forms, statements and grant amounts.
  Informational Documents: Contains informational documents relating to grants, scholarships, programs and the foundation itself.
  Organizational Documents: Contains internal documents such as by laws, computer databases, and committee papers.
  - Financial Documents 1994-2001
    - 990 Form 1999-2000. 2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 990 Form 2000-2001. 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Amazon Foundation Check Requests. 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Amazon Foundation Grants. 1994-1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Financial Statements. 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Grants History. 1994-2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Informational Documents 1998-2002
    - Amazon Adventurers Information. undated, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Amazon Foundation Brochures. 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Amazon Fund. undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Amazon Fund. 1998-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Grant Information. undated, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Great Summer Information. undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Scholarship Information. undated, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Organizational Documents 1994-2002
    - Board of Trustees. 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - By Laws. undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Computer Database. 2002 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Furniture Donations. undated, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Scholarship Committee. 1994-2002 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Summer Enrichment Breakfast. 2001 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Thank You notes. undated, 1995-1999 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Award Files 1990-2002
  Arrangement: Alphabetical. This series contains files relating to awards given by the Amazon Foundation. Included in some files are correspondence, printed materials and photographs. Some materials are in Spanish. It is divided into two subseries.
  Grants: Contains information on grants awarded by the foundation to individuals and other groups.
  Scholarships: Contains information on scholarships awarded by the foundation to individual students and their institutions.
  - Grants 1990-2002
    - American Friends Service Committee. undated, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Angel Charity. undated, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Arizona Children's Association. undated, 1996-1999 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Arizona Citizen Action. undated, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Arizona State Schools for the Deaf and the Blind. undated, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Arizona Women's Political Caucus. 1999-2001 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Astrae Lesbian Action Foundation. undated, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - ASUA Pride Alliance. undated, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - ASUA Women's Resource Center. undated, 1999-2002 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Asylum Program of Southern Arizona. undated, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Black Women's Task Force. undated, 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Border Volunteer Corps. undated, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Borderlands Theater. undated, 1997-2002 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Boys and Girls Club of Santa Cruz County. undated, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Brewster Center. 1991-2002 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Casa de Esperanza. undated, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Center for the Contemplative Mind in Society. undated, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Central Arts Collective. 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Child Abuse Survivors Network. 1995 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Children to Children. 1995 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Christmas in April. 1996 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - City Life News and Publishing. undated, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Colditz, Hazel (The Integration of SHE). undated, 2001-2002 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Community Shares of Southern Arizona. undated, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - CR Collective. undated, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Dance Matrix. undated, 1992-2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Desert Doula Childbirth Services. undated, 1996-2002 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Desert Voices. 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Dewey, Janice (Nancy Mairs Documentary). 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Dunbar Coalition, Inc. 1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Environmental Flying Services. 1994-1997 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Equipoise Gallery, Inc. 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Equity Institute. 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Ferguson, Kathryn (Walking Woman). undated, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Fish Out of Water Films. undated, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Forest Guardians. 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Funders for Lesbian and Gay Issues. undated, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Green, Talia (Israel Project). 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Green Thursday Theatre Project. 2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Hammond, Harmony (University of Arizona Art Department). undated, 1993-2002 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - House of Hope. undated, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - In the West Productions. undated, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - International Women's Day Committee. undated, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Inzalaco, Lorraine (Visible for a Change Exhibit). undated, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Jewish Family and Children's Service. undated, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Kore Press. undated, 1996-2002 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Las Sinfronteras. undated, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Lesbian Avengers. undated, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Lesbian Cancer and Health Project. 1998-2000 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender and Straight Alliance Fund. 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Lesbian Health Fair. 2002 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Lesbian Looks Film and Video Series. undated, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - LULAC (League of United Latin American Citizens). 1995 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Makino, Yuri (Media Arts). undated, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Miles Exploratory Learning Center. 1995-1998 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Our Town Family Center. undated, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Pan Left Productions. 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Peaceful Warrior Project. undated, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - PHASE (Project for Homemakers in Arizona Seeking Employment). undated, 1999-2002 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Pima County Tucson Women's Commission. undated, 1995-2002 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Planned Parenthood. 1998-2002 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Primavera Foundation. 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Primavera Services. undated, 1994-2002 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - The Promotora Institute: The Way of the Heart. undated, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Proyecto Comadres. 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Pueblo High School. 1995 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Queer Voice. 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Randolph Soccer Club. 2000 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Saheli: Sisters in Action. undated, 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Salt of the Earth Labor College. 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Scouting for All. 2001 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Small Discretionary Grants. 2001-2002 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Soundoff Tucson Healthcare. 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Southern Arizona AIDS Foundation. 1998-2002 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Southern Arizona Alliance for Economic Justice. undated, 1995-2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Southern Arizona Center Against Sexual Assault. undated, 1995-2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Southern Arizona Center Against Sexual Assault. 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Southern Arizona Gender Alliance. undated, 1999-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Southwest Alliance to Resist Militarization. undated, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Southwest Center for Economic Integrity. 2002 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Southwest Institute for Research on Women. 1994-2002 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - TECLA (Tucson Ecumenical Council Legal Assistance). undated, 1994-1999 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Terrill, Ceiridwen (Cumberland Island Project). 1998 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - TGNet Arizona. undated, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Third Street Kids. 1995 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Tucson Coalition Against Star Wars. 2001 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Tucson Jewish Film Festival. 1998 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Tucson Miracles Basketball Program. 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Tucson V-Day. 2000-2001 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Tucson Women Take Back the Night. 1995-1998 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Tucson Women's Artist Collective. undated, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Tucson Youth at Risk. undated, 1994-1998 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Tucson/Pima Arts Council. 1999-2001 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Unexpected Company. 1996 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - University of Arizona Black Alumni Dinner. 1996 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - University of Arizona Breastfeeding Support Project. 1994 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - University of Arizona Center for Creative Photography. undated, 1994-2001 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - University of Arizona Center for Disability Related Resources. undated, 1996-2000 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - University of Arizona Committee on LGBT Studies. undated, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - University of Arizona Department of Media Arts. 1996-2000 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - University of Arizona Latin American Area Center. undated, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - University of Arizona Poetry Center. 1999 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - University of Arizona Sierra Vista Campus. 1995-1996 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - University of Arizona Urban Bush Women Program. undated, 1993-1997 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - University of Arizona Women's Studies Advisory Council Plaza of Honor Project. undated, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Victim Investigation Information Services. 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Weisman, Alan (Gaviotas). 1995 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Wingspan. undated, 1994-2002 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Wingspan Domestic Violence Project. undated, 1995-2002 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - WISE (Women's Inititative for Self Employment). undated, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Woman to Woman Program (Tucson Medical Center Foundation). 1994 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Woman Vision Productions. undated, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Women and Their Work. 1996 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Women Builders. undated, 19969-2002 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Women Make Music. undated, 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Women's Educational Media Project. 1995 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Women's Foundation of Southern Arizona. undated, 1994-2002 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Women's Funding Network. 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Women's Transition Project (Bisbee, AZ). undated, 1999-2002 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - YWCA Tucson. undated, 1994-2001 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Zuni Avenue Peace Center. undated, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - ZUZI! Move It Dance Company. undated, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Scholarships 1994-2002
    - Langston University (Lewis, Dena). 1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Origins Society. 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Pima Community College Fundraising Training. undated, 1999-2002 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Pima Community College Scholarship Letters. undated, 1999-2002 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Scholarship Transmittal Letters. undated, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Summer Enrichment Transmittal Letters and Receipts. undated, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - University of Arizona Scholarship Letters. undated, 1999-2002 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Photographic Materials 2001
  This series contains photographs of foundation functions and a photo album.
  - Photographs - General. undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Photo Album - Summer Enrichment Brunch. 2001 (Box 4)